KARTHIKEYAN NATARAJAN

TECHNOLOGY AND DELIVERY LEADER

4616 UNITED LN, PLANO, TX 75024 ◆+1 (214) 801-2984 ◆ karthiknatarajanmba@gmail.com ◆ http://www.karthiknatarajan.in

PROFILE SUMMARY

A multi-faceted passionate techno-functional leader with 17+ years of experience in technology, product and program management leadership in building, scaling and transforming complex business applications and product platforms to achieve business objectives. Possess the vision needed to see the most challenging, and exciting possibilities clearly and deliver complex large-scale programs and enterprise change from strategy through execution in fast paced and ambiguous environments. Excellent communicator and trusted technical partner.

SKILLS

- Delivery Transformation
- Strategic Leadership
- Business Relationships
- Team Building
- People Development
- Conflict Management
- Presentation Skills
- Change & Risk Management

- Technical Leadership
- Program Management
- Planning And Execution
- Quantitative Skills
- Goals And Objectives
- Costing & Budgeting
- Forecasting
- Negotiation

- Agile Methodologies
- Cloud Computing
- Amazon Web Services (AWS)
- Web & Mobile Development
- Java & Database Tools
- JavaScript & JS Frameworks
- Artificial Intelligence (AI)
- Machine Learning (ML)

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

AMAZON.COM, SEATTLE, WA

Oct. 2021 - Till Date

Principal Technical Program Manager | Sr. TPM

Oct. 2021 - Till Date

- Provided technical leadership and strategic direction for end-to-end product, delivery and technical oversight of capabilities for cross-organizational programs in Alexa and Amazon Digital Businesses
- Identified areas of synergies between different product offerings in Amazon and executed a successful convergence program to streamline the products and improved customer experience
- Led the teams in mitigating risks, establishing and achieving key metrics, achieving product quality goals, maintaining schedules and budgets, managing escalations and facilitating efficient execution
- Partnered with Engineering, Product, and Leadership to streamline processes, simplify execution, and manage on-time releases. Set up best practices.
- Hired and developed talents; Built a healthy work environment both for the immediate organization and broader Amazon by mentoring, and contributing to promo process and talent reviews.
- Help architect the executional framework for cross-functional alignment. Worked with teams to develop and deploy strategies to scale processes as the program evolves; continually improved the processes/mechanisms.
- Led regular communication with teammates, partners, and leadership and conducted periodic reviews with executive leadership teams.

Principal Technical Program Manager | Lead TPM

Aug. 2019 - Sept. 2021

Client: Citibank, Irving, TX

- Technical Program Management Leader responsible for the delivery of critical cross-organizational technology transformation programs
- Collaborated across a matrixed organization of Product Management, Architecture, Engineering,
 Design, Data science and Support for the successful execution of program objectives
- Communicated effectively, driven consensus and influence at all levels and across functions within the organization
- Tracked KPI and OKRs for added visibility into project deliveries, team performance against Goals set for the year
- Managed risks, issues & dependencies in the program successfully by identifying, evaluating, tracking and mitigating them in a timely fashion
- Hired, developed TPMs and established high performing work culture & environment for the group
- Managed financial forecasts, cost assumptions, and provided on-going reconciliation of resources and other related project expenditures

AMERICAN AIRLINES, FORT WORTH, TX

Oct. 2015 - Aug. 2019

IT Portfolio Manager | Technical Program Manager

Oct. 2015 - Aug. 2019

- Technical Program Manager responsible for strategy, execution and implementation of various projects and programs for Shopping portfolio.
- Led multiple multi-million-dollar programs that delivered on critical business goals and created delightful customer experience in Web and Mobile Platforms
- Successfully managed, mentored, and trained cross functional agile teams and led Agile, DevOps,
 Cloud Computing and Delivery Transformation in the Customer Technology Organization
- Hired and mentored Project managers in Shopping Portfolio and responsible for managing Portfolio's Roadmap, budget, cost/schedule, reporting, and change management
- Drove simplification, optimization, and quality of IT systems and processes by adopting best practices in software design, development and program management

GALLOP SOLUTIONS INC., IRVING, TX

May 2011 - Sep 2015

Agile Project Manager | Scrum Master | Technical Project Manager

May 2011 - Sep 2015

Clients: American Airlines, Ft. Worth, TX & Harley Davidson Financial Services, Plano, TX

- Managed multiple large scale Web development and Infrastructure projects (\$1-6 Million USD) such as Content Management System (CMS) upgrade and saved 50% of Content editor's manual effort
- Managed wing to wing execution, issue resolution, program risks, and resource allocation and vendor relationship for product lifecycle management platform
- Managed client expectations and ensured customer satisfaction through outstanding communication regarding project scope, schedule, and direction
- Identified and managed Risks and Issues and maintained smooth execution of the Project

• Responsible for technical program management, engagement management, software development, product strategy, cross functional team leadership, stakeholder management, business development, financial and people management

COGNIZANT TECH SOLUTIONS US CORP., TEANECK, NJ

Apr. 2007 - Apr. 2011

Associate | Technical Project Manager

Apr. 2007 - Apr. 2011

Clients: PepsiCo, Plano, TX & Alliance Data, Richardson, TX

- Lead a team of over 12 analysts (on-shore and off-shore) across multiple projects and delivered projects successfully exceeding client's expectation; worked closely with the Business and IT as an application subject matter expert
- Collaborated with Client Project Managers to develop estimates, plan, project schedules and resource allocation models while ensuring conformance to established project management process and methodology
- Communicated the status of project throughout all phases; including completed tasks, pending deliverable, and outstanding items
- Identified risks, issues & bottlenecks and resolved them by working closely with stakeholders

COGNIZANT TECHNOLOGY SOLUTIONS INDIA PVT. LIMITED, CHENNAI, INDIA Aug 2005 - Apr 2007

Programmer Analyst | Technical Project Lead

Aug 2005 – Apr 2007

Clients: British American Tobacco, Malaysia and Mitsubishi, 3M & Centrica Plc., Chennai, India

- Led and managed the Handheld Point of Sale (PoS) upgrade project for British American Tobacco Malaysia client in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia
- Led a team of 6-9 people from India and executed delivery of various technical projects from Strategy to Implementation and Support for various clients across the globe.
- Trained and mentored new team members

EDUCATION

MBA - Innovation & Entrepreneurship

Aug 2013 - May 2015

THE UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT DALLAS, RICHARDSON, TX

Bachelors in Electronics & Communication Engineering

Aug 2001 - May 2005

ANNA UNIVERSITY, CHENNAI, INDIA

CERTIFICATIONS

PMI-Certified Projet Management Professional (PMP)	Mar. 2013
Scrum Alliance Certified Scrum Master (CSM)	Dec. 2012
AWS Certified Solutions Architect – Associate	Jul. 2019
Machine Learning (Stanford University)	Apr. 2020
ICAgile Certified Professional in Agile Coaching (ICP-ACC)	Apr. 2015
ICAgile Certified Professional in Agile Team Facilitation (ICP-ATF)	Nov. 2015
Business System Analysis & Business Process Management	Mar. 2013
Computational Thinking for Problem Solving (Penn Engineering)	Apr. 2020